<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Cases on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cases on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 14:57:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/book/cases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A brief history of LLM tooling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/brief-llm-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 14:57:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/brief-llm-tool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In order to illustrate the development of technology through tracking the development of LLM related tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2023 (check) ChatGPT came out.
Within days people from around the world were using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAG - companies
Langchain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP and A2A&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP spinoffs&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How My Site Got Hacked</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/how-my-site-got-hacked/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 15:35:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/how-my-site-got-hacked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;detection&#34;&gt;Detection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have acted on the first signals more aggressively. But let’s talk about that later in this story.
Here is the story of my site being infected with malware, viewed by a professional cloud security expert. So I am going to apply all that cloud security theory to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hack led to business damage at the end of one of my webinars. In 2016, on a Friday, I did a webinar, at the end of which I had two links to my site as a call to action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Small Example of Cloud Native Development</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/tutorial-cloud-native/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 23:29:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/tutorial-cloud-native/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cloud-native software development enables new practices. But it also requires them. It is a new level of working. However, putting all these new practices together requires integrating a lot of pieces.
To illustrate this new approach, I have started to develop a minimal application. Although minimal, I run it in production. Its basic function is to regularly pull out data from an air quality sensor into a cloud-based database. Together it is a few hundred lines of code.
Here are the major features of the example:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Cloud Sprawl in 2012</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/stopping-senseless-sprawl-of-private-clouds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 07:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/stopping-senseless-sprawl-of-private-clouds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even in a cloud world, reducing server count is a lofty goal in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, you would be paying for all those servers anyway. Understand that sticking all your servers in a private cloud makes them more flexible, but not necessarily more efficient or cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2012 I did an interview with a guy who has a full time job in keeping those server counts down. Ron Kaminski is a capacity planner at Kimberly Clark Corporation (KCC). This interview is a composite of several conversations I had with Ron at the annual Computer Measurement Group (CMG) conferences, and a number of messages Ron wrote.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
