<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Power on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Power on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 20:32:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/book/power/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Janvandijk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/janvandijk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 20:32:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/janvandijk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Summary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;p2 power is the ability to shape events.
p3 social vs natural vs technical power
p3 dialectical view. technology is a mediator, tech and society influence one another
pve: AI is now being trained on how AI is being used by humans. Which is better than AI being trained on whatever AI is generating.
p12 feedback loops in power: natural power is used to get more power (chain reaction). Power to versus power over.
p13 humans control natural power
p14 digital infrastructures transform: make things possible that weren&amp;rsquo;t before; automation of transformation. Control that is possible as a result of this. Tech introduces new stakeholders to the game (e.g. ultrasound, takes agency away from the pregnant woman), and shifts power.
p16 preventing is also power
p16 power always meets resistance and counterpower. Voorbeeld counterpower van buschauffeurs die gecontroleerd worden.
p16 power is a capacity (of negatief bekeken: een dreigement is ook macht)
p18 le pouvoir public
p19 is technolgoy zelf ook een actor?
p19 capacity van actoren, om te beinvloeden in een context teneinde ..
p23 is power positive or negative?
p24 game theory; political power comes from the barrel of a gun.
p25 voorbeeld. providers dwingen gebruikers om voorwaarden te accepteren. Niet eens eenmalig, maar creeping up. Hier zit een prisoners dilemma in?
p25 micro = humans, meso is groepen, instituties, macro is big tech en overheid. Ik denk zelf dat er verschil is onder en boven de 150 pax.
p27 belemmeren van keuze is ook een verschijning van macht. Terwijl grotere keuze vaak als meer keuze wordt gepresenteerd, maar dat niet altijd is.
p27 creators and users can have shifting foci of power
p27 voorbeeld internet, wie is er de baas over? private, public? tegelijkertijd is internet een middel tot subversiviteit tegen de centrale machten. Als zodanig is het internet nauweijiks meer te controleren.
p29 nudging is ook een vorm van macht.
p30 technologie wordt van een tool van individuen tot een tool voor organisaties (denk polders en irrigatiesystemen)
p31 ownership implies control (in hoeverre is dat zo)
p44 tech means artifacts
p45 tech implies skills, and in particular transferable (learnable) skills. If tech (a.o. AI) is an actor, it has a symbiotic relation with other actors (the skilled persons). Scalability shifts the power from the craftsmen to the capitalist who can bring together a: the scale, b: the investment for skills.
p45 socially transmittable skills require language, or at least some form of shared common concepts (symbol making).
p46 tools give power because they afford transformations, however this notion has critiques. e.g. it excludes morality.
p47 it also does not talk about second order effects (not anticipated now) and third order effects (not anticipated for the future)
p48 technology is an active mediator
p64 actors: creators, makers, users
p65 technology involves making choices within constraints. If you do X, you cannot do Y.
p67 the invention of capitalism (voc?). Who rules the internet? big tech, or big gov?
p78 mediation - introduction
p81 technological determinism -&amp;gt; tech determines social change (diamat?)
p81 does society use technology, or does technology use society (link: the selfish meme)
p92 techno optimism: societal problems can be solved by tech
p92 technology is a social construct - with a life of its own
p93 because one man has invented how to make a sword, the other has the have one too, even if you do not plan to use it. This implies that the sword itself has power, because it forces behaviour.
p84 fallacy of lone inventor: all tech is a social construct.
p85 ontwerp, versus productie versus gebruik. Met name bij sofware is productie niet langer een machtsfactor.
p86 (link met text niet helemaal duidelijk) stabilisatie en closure versus cambrian explosion. Voorbeeld al die computer firma&amp;rsquo;s: Prime, Harris, Electrologica, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Power</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/intro-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:31:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/intro-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Power is a concept that is widely used and ill defined. Many philosophers have discussed it, but not one definition really stands out.
Before we attempt to define power formally, let&amp;rsquo;s see how the word in used in everyday IT situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding power in IT is not just academic. As the examples show it is crucial in understanding how IT works, and creates value and risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cloud architect held significant power in deciding which platforms the organization would adopt for its digital transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated deployment pipelines gave development teams the power to release software faster and with fewer errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legacy systems often retain unexpected power in large organizations, simply because so many critical processes still depend on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regulators have the power to halt digital initiatives if data protection requirements are not met.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By owning the central identity management service, the security team had the power to control access across the entire infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outages at major cloud providers show how concentrated power in digital infrastructures can lead to systemic risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CIO used the power of budget approval to steer the enterprise toward adopting more secure infrastructure patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power struggles between central IT and business units can delay the rollout of shared infrastructure services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With real-time observability tools, operations teams gained the power to detect and respond to incidents before users were affected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open-source community can collectively wield more power than a single vendor when shaping the direction of a software tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these examples, we can see certain recurring features of power in the context of IT and digital infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The moral necessity of talking about power</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/ethics-of-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 20:30:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/ethics-of-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For many people, the word power has a negative connotation.
They&amp;rsquo;d rather avoid using power altogether.
I can feel that, and I can definitely feel that about the abuse of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But does that make it unethical to talk about power?
Power is everywhere, and conflict too. There is no society without a power structure.
There are always differences of opinions in any group, if only to decide when to have lunch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Governance over IT, an example</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/governance-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 11:07:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/governance-example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shared resources can lead to conflicts.
If the capacity runs out, somebody will feel the pain at the expense of somebody else.
This conflict will be resolved in one way or another.
Without other arrangements, the stakeholder with the most power wins.
This is not necessarily the best outcome for the organization as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this, I gave ChatGPT the following prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a business case story about the conflict over shared computing resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Where the buck stops</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/buck-stops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 21:08:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/buck-stops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The US president Harry S. Truman famously had a sign on his desk that said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buck stops here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This refers to the process of &amp;ldquo;passing up the buck&amp;rdquo;, meaning to escalate decisions to the next higher level in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truman implied that he took responsibility but also that this is where power comes from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an essential part of governance, and this vertical line of responsibility represents one way of looking at it.
We can trace how this works in the following risk management example.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positions of Power in IT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 11:06:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspirations of Digital Infrastructures at Scale is to equip you with the tools to shape and drive change in your professional environment—especially when your goal is to lead a transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every stakeholder has power. Here I want to highlight two important positions of influence in IT where technology meets power are architects and auditors/assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IT architects are builders. They design new applications, platforms, and infrastructures that enable businesses to operate more effectively. A CRM system, for example, is not just a technical solution—it transforms workflows, communication, and decision-making. Similarly, infrastructure architects create digital foundations that accelerate the deployment of such applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power Flows</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/power-mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/power-mediation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Power does not automatically flow from those that have it to those that are influenced by it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they say in dutch, quoting the poet Willem Elsschot: &amp;ldquo;tussen droom en daad staan wetten in de weg, en praktische bezwaren&amp;rdquo;. (&amp;ldquo;between dream and deed stand laws in the way, and practical objections&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to understand this. If we want to exercise power, we need to understand the intermediaries. If we want to subvert power, the intermediaries are one of our disruptive points.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promise Multiparty</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/promise-multiparty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 13:29:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/promise-multiparty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Intermediaries, brokers. 3 actortypes (or more)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An intermediary adds value between client/server, source/sink
I.e. index, filter, conversion, (de)couple
(e.g. Relate to ’broker’)
Indexen
Gebruikersadministratie, ten behoeve van autorisatie en TTP diensten
Abonnementadministratie, welke afnemers of belangstellenden zijn er?
Bronindex, welke bronnen hebben informatie over een bepaald sofinummer (search engine)?
Functionaliteit
formaat conversie, filtering
vraag/aanbod matching
Performance
verdelen en routeren van berichten, multicasting
aggregatie
caching
bundeling van afspraken (bijv. SLA)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distributor/directory
authorization
choice / arbitration / load balancer
service integration
pubsub. Intermediary holds source and subscriber directories. Notice the various commitments that can be made. Examples: newsletter, podcast subscription
multicast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;subscription toepassing: chatbots streaming?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who made podcasting big?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/the-tipping-point-for-podcasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2005 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/the-tipping-point-for-podcasting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Podcasting has its own digital infrastructures, for example in hosting them.
Let&amp;rsquo;s look at how podcasting has grown, and what made it take off anyway?
Many actors influence each other here, and the state of the art of the technology also has an impact on growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose a hundred people get told by an enthusiastic friend to try podcasting.
Of these, ten don’t have any hardware on which they can play the podcasts.
So the rest goes online, and tries to find interesting content, but only 50 people can find a directory in which they can even start to look for podcasts that they like. Only 40 people then find content that they sufficiently like.
Ten people drop out because they find loading the content too complicated. Of these, another ten find out that the files are too big for the hardware they have (for example in 2005, they just had a simple MP3 player, no iPod or similar).
Of the ones left, another five don’t have the patience for the downloads (we are talking dial-up internet access for a lot of people here, still).
If you have been keeping tabs: we are down to 25 people who are capable and willing to regularly listen to podcasts. Now suppose each of these tells four friends, on the average. That means we are back to a hundred.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disruptive Technologies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/powershift-disruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 21:25:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/powershift-disruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Technologies are often called disruptive.
But what makes a technology truly disruptive?
What has made the PC a disruptive technology? Or artificial intelligence, for that matter?
And at what time did it become a disruptive technology?
While many would accept that AI was a very disruptive technology starting from 2022 onwards,
most of it was available much earlier. GenAI, chatbots, etc.
Think of ELIZA, the 60s era psychology chatbot by Joseph Weizenbaum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Actors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/international-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/international-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The international arena has many actors that can influence digital infrastructures. But opinions differ on what the important ones are, or even what the relevant ones are.
But the international arena matters, because
by the nature of scaling, very few digital infrastructures are influenced by a single national actor only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word of clarification: I am using the word international here to mean all nations in the world, and their interrelations.
In US vernacular, the word international appears to mean all nations, except the US.
Instead, the word global is used to mean all nations, including the US.
An example implication of this is that a US company would only consider ISO standards to be relevant to them if they also have operations outside the US.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
