<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 09:18:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/book/risk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk is the flip side of value. For everything that is of value, there can be circumstances threatening that value.
While value is realized in the past and the present, risk is what can happen with that value in the &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk in a digital world is not always easy to think through. While we can borrow a lot from the real world, certain important differences exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of every risk assessment there is the thing we worry about the most: the &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;.
In a digital world, this is often the &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of business-critical data, like our database of customers. Think of data that we have a compliance obligation on, such as personal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Security Assets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/assets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 08:37:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/assets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s dive a little deeper into assets.
The most relevant asset in information security is data.
That is what users of information care about most.
In addition, we can also see the processing power that we need as an asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of data assets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A customer record in a business system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An MRI scan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A browser cookie (on the server)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A logfile entry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can guess from these examples, many involve regulatory concerns due to the type of data that they consist of.
One of the tasks of a risk analyst is to figure out what regulations apply exactly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Suffers?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/who-suffers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 21:27:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/who-suffers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have found that no discussion on risk is going to lead anywhere if it does not make clear who suffers from it.
Make clear who has the pain.
For my phone and laptop it is easy: if I lose them, I suffer.
In a larger organization it is less clear.
Suppose a server dies.
Whose application then no longer runs?
Who has to pay for a new server?
This gets increasingly harder if we are talking about shared services, because the owner and the consumer are now decoupled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controls</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/controls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 21:39:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/controls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft: Countermeasure (or control). A safeguard that addresses a threat and mitigates risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what other assets?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where did that file go?
Where did you leave that address?
Who changed your password?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have assets and risks identified, we think of ways to minimize these risks.
Those ways are called controls or measures.
If you have read through an IT risk management book, many of these should be familiar.
For the rest of you, here is a brief outline of some control examples for data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/mitigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 09:39:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/mitigation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;walk in with well spelled out risks, a clear connection to business impact, data, a mitigation plan, and measurable targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Providing third-party assurance enables the board to deliver on its risk management responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What about AI Risks?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/querying-ai-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 07:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/querying-ai-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While Artificial Intelligence, especially the generative type, is a highly disruptive form of IT innovation, its risk management still follows the same basic principles.
We just need to extend those principles to new forms of data and software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the assets?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the vulnerabilities and threats to it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the damage that this can bring, realistically?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s see how what the AI specifics are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ai-assets&#34;&gt;AI Assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s focus on the AI assets that are the product of deep learning.
Deep learning neural networks have represented a shift in AI technology.
Before that, symbolic AI was more common.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Is Trust</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/what-is-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 10:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/what-is-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trust is an essential element in any collaboration.
We want to trust things, people, and organizations to do the right thing, to keep their promises.
Without trust, we will not be able to have confidence in the contribution of others, and that is a risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything we don&amp;rsquo;t trust is a risk.
Anytime we assume trust that is not warranted is also a risk.
That is one of the core concepts of Zero Trust Security Architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lean Risk and Economics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/lean-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 19:58:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/lean-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the moment a security vulnerability is discovered, it represents a negative value to its potential victims.
When it gets exploited, it can lead to loss of data or loss of integrity of the data.
This in turn impacts the victim&amp;rsquo;s business processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if personal data is leaked, reputations will be damaged, financial losses and fines can be expected. Credit card abuse forms another example of loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;damage potential&amp;rdquo; increases as the vulnerability becomes well-known, progressing from nation state actors, to organized crime, to script kiddies, just to name one example pathway.
At first, few people know about it, but gradually more people will be able to inflict damage with it.
Over time, each step adds to the likelihood of that vulnerability being exploited and causing real damage.
The likelihood starts at near zero, and ends at close to 100% as the vulnerability is completely public.
This only stops when an investment is made to mitigate the vulnerability, for example by updating the software.
And hopefully, that investment is less costly than the damage potential.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrofitting Zero Trust on an existing application: an illustration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 14:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Architecture is an approach to better cybersecurity. To many, it seems daunting to implement. But it does not have to be hard to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this hypothetical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an application with hundreds of thousands of sensitive records, let’s say client records. We assume that in this example it seems hard to implement MFA (Multi Factor Authentication) on it. What other controls can you implement to reduce the assumed trust? We can use the Kipling method, which is at the core of Zero Trust architectures, to engineer better controls. In short, the Kipling method is about the &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo;, etcetera of allowed communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A guide to digital sovereignty, autonomy, and business resilience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/guide-autonomy-resilience/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 14:57:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/guide-autonomy-resilience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(First public draft)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you are part of the government of an average nation, and you have just realized that IT has become a substantial factor in your operation.
Or you have a similar position in a manufacturing industry, or in the financial sector.
As IT increased in volume, you have tried to keep its costs down, it was just a facility.
Outsourcing to more experienced partners was an option, and so was the use of cloud computing, for example for your Office applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Uneasy Relationship Between Compliance and Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/uneasy-compliance-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 09:18:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/uneasy-compliance-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For people who care about risk in IT, compliance is a mixed blessing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compliance in IT generally means compliance with regulations that are set up to reduce risk, for example across a chain of companies.
A great example is the PCI/DSS regulation, which governs everybody who touches a credit card transaction.
The objective of this regulation is to protect card holders and card issuers from credit card fraud.
The reason why the regulation exists in the first place is because negligence at one actor can lead to damages at another actor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
