<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/book/risk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a digital world, it is not always easy to think through what risk is. While we can borrow a lot from the real world, certain important differences exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of every risk assessment there is the thing we worry about the most: the &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a digital world, this is often the &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Think business critical data, like our database of customers. Think data that we have a compliance obligation on, such as personal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrofitting Zero Trust on an existing application: an illustration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 14:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Architecture is an approach to better cybersecurity. To many, it seems daunting to implement. But it does not have to be hard to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this hypothetical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an application with hundreds of thousands of sensitive records, let’s say client records. We assume that in this example it seems hard to implement MFA (Multi Factor Authentication) on it. What other controls can you implement to reduce the assumed trust? We can use the Kipling method, which is at the core of Zero Trust architectures, to engineer better controls. In short, the Kipling method is about the &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo;, etcetera of allowed communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
