<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.6</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 19:58:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Risk</title>
      <link>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk is the flip side of value. For everything that is of value, there can be circumstances threatening that value.
While value is realized in the past and the present, risk is what can happen with that value in the &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk in a digital world is not always easy to think through. While we can borrow a lot from the real world, certain important differences exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of every risk assessment there is the thing we worry about the most: the &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;.
In a digital world, this is often the &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of business-critical data, like our database of customers. Think of data that we have a compliance obligation on, such as personal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Suffers?</title>
      <link>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/who-suffers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 21:27:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/who-suffers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have found that no discussion on risk is going to lead anywhere if it does not make clear who suffers from it.
Make clear who has the pain.
For my phone and laptop it is easy: if I lose them, I suffer.
In a larger organization it is less clear.
Suppose a server dies.
Whose application then no longer runs?
Who has to pay for a new server?
This gets increasingly harder if we are talking about shared services, because the owner and the consumer are now decoupled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lean Risk and Economics</title>
      <link>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/lean-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 19:58:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/lean-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the moment a security vulnerability is discovered, it represents a negative value to its potential victims.
When it gets exploited, it can lead to loss of data or loss of integrity of the data.
This in turn impacts the victim&amp;rsquo;s business processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if personal data is leaked, reputations will be damaged, financial losses and fines can be expected. Credit card abuse forms another example of loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;damage potential&amp;rdquo; increases as the vulnerability becomes well-known, progressing from nation state actors, to organized crime, to script kiddies, just to name one example pathway.
At first, few people know about it, but gradually more people will be able to inflict damage with it.
Over time, each step adds to the likelihood of that vulnerability being exploited and causing real damage.
The likelihood starts at near zero, and ends at close to 100% as the vulnerability is completely public.
This only stops when an investment is made to mitigate the vulnerability, for example by updating the software.
And hopefully, that investment is less costly than the damage potential.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrofitting Zero Trust on an existing application: an illustration</title>
      <link>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 14:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://digitalinfrastructures.nl/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Architecture is an approach to better cybersecurity. To many, it seems daunting to implement. But it does not have to be hard to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this hypothetical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an application with hundreds of thousands of sensitive records, let’s say client records. We assume that in this example it seems hard to implement MFA (Multi Factor Authentication) on it. What other controls can you implement to reduce the assumed trust? We can use the Kipling method, which is at the core of Zero Trust architectures, to engineer better controls. In short, the Kipling method is about the &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo;, etcetera of allowed communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
