<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Risks of digital infrastructures on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 07:40:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/book/risk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk is the flip side of value. For everything that is of value, there can be circumstances endangering that value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk in a digital world is not always easy to think through. While we can borrow a lot from the real world, certain important differences exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of every risk assessment there is the thing we worry about the most: the &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;.
In a digital world, this is often the &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of business critical data, like our database of customers. Think data that we have a compliance obligation on, such as personal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Querying Ai Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/querying-ai-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 07:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/querying-ai-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While Artificial Intelligence, especially the generative type, is a really disruptive form of IT innovation, its risk management still follows the same basic principles.
We just need to extend those principles to new forms of data and software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the assets?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the vulnerabilities and threats to it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the damage that this can bring, realistically?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s see how what the AI specifics are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ai-assets&#34;&gt;AI Assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s focus on the AI assets that are the product of deep learning.
Deep learning neural networks have represented a shift in AI technology.
Before that, symbolic AI was more common.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Suffers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/who-suffers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 21:27:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/who-suffers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-suffers&#34;&gt;Who Suffers?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found that no discussion on risk is going to lead anywhere if it does not make clear who suffers from it.
For my phone and laptop it is easy: if I lose them, I suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;external-victims&#34;&gt;External victims&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;who suffers? externalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;assets&#34;&gt;Assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vulnerabilities-and-threats&#34;&gt;Vulnerabilities and threats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(examples of all)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what other assets?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrofitting Zero Trust on an existing application: an illustration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 14:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Architecture is an approach to better cybersecurity. To many, it seems daunting to implement. But it does not have to be hard to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this hypothetical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an application with hundreds of thousands of sensitive records, let’s say client records. We assume that in this example it seems hard to implement MFA (Multi Factor Authentication) on it. What other controls can you implement to reduce the assumed trust? We can use the Kipling method, which is at the core of Zero Trust architectures, to engineer better controls. In short, the Kipling method is about the &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo;, etcetera of allowed communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
