<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Peter&#39;s Griddle on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peter&#39;s Griddle on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 20:34:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Elements of Digitalinfrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/elements-of-digitalinfrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 20:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/elements-of-digitalinfrastructures/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Elements of Cloud Security</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 22:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;five-elements-of-cloud-security&#34;&gt;Five elements of cloud security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, IT security started with &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure security&lt;/strong&gt;. Just protecting the data center was good enough. But that was before we had data communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When data started to escape the confines of the data center we needed to protect it. Typically through encryption. Hence we need &lt;strong&gt;data security&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the world wide web developed, we saw applications being exposed to it, and frankly, be vulnerable. So that is when &lt;strong&gt;application security&lt;/strong&gt; started to become more important.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How AI Can Help IT Risk Classification</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 19:45:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How cool would it be to let an AI do some of the grunt work in analysing the risk of applications and services. This has the potential to speed up the work of risk assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, does it work in practice? Well, here is an example of AI-assisted risk classification. I downloaded some of the entries in the Dutch &lt;a href=&#34;https://algoritmes.overheid.nl/en&#34;&gt;algorithm register&lt;/a&gt;, which is a public register of systems that use algorithms. For each entry about 30 fields are available, including name, classification, owner, et cetera.
Some of the systems in the registry are AI-based. Indeed, we have AI to help check on AI&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying technology by following a system</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/technical-meta-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/technical-meta-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How to fix the WiFi? How to find a new phone for grandma?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying technology follows certain rules. However, many people only have an intuitive understanding of these rules. As a result technology is not optimally applied.
By understanding how applying technology really works, you can be more effective, more efficient, reduce waste, and overall do a better job. It takes just a few simple steps to improve any attempt at applying technology. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on information technology here, though most principles have wider applicability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Actors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/international-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/international-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The international arena has many actors that can influence digital infrastructures. But opinions differ on what the important ones are, or even what the relevant ones are.
By the nature of scaling, very few digital infrastructures are influenced by national actors only. The international arena is complex, and there are even conflicting views on how it is made up.
These conflicting views can best be seen as maps of the territory. And as I have mentioned earlier, a map is only relevant for a specific purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The US Air Force Zero Trust Strategy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 12:26:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Who is really doing Zero Trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the US Air Force is. Here is my summary, with some comments, of their strategy document for the benefit of my Certificate of Competence in Zero Trust (CCZT) learners. In fact, this is an edited version of a conversation we had during one of our classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the full strategy &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20API%20Reference%20Architecture%202.0.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the current roadmap &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20Enterprise%20Zero%20Trust%20Roadmap%20and%20Release%20Notes_v2.0.pdf?ver=36cbAKNEe7JiRVAPFwWepg%3d%3d&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, all linked from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the fundamental first important point about the strategy document is that it exists at all. There is an actual organization of significant size that has a strategy and is implementing it. Many can learn from this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Infrastructures - the graphic novel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 14:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the draft design of the graphic novel version of this book, which may or may not happen..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;p&lt;img alt=&#34;digital world cyberpunk&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/dig-inf-front-page1.png&#34; title=&#34;With a little help from Dall-e&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can We Achieve Autonomy Over Our Digital Infrastructures?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 22:04:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-our-own-cloud-kootwijk-rethinking-digital-sovereignty&#34;&gt;Building Our Own Cloud Kootwijk: Rethinking Digital Sovereignty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, we are currently engaged in a heated debate about the undesirable dominance of big tech, particularly over a significant portion of the digital infrastructure of the Dutch government. This includes email, file storage, and many other forms of digital storage and processing—most of which are handled by American big tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure a similar debate is going on in many other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mermaid diagram example</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 09:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A diagram should automagically appear here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;%%  icons from https://iconify.design
architecture-beta
    group api(Storage)[API]

    service db(database)[Database] in api
    service disk1(disk)[Storage] in api
    service disk2(disk)[Storage] in api
    service server(server)[Server] in api

    db:L -- R:server
    disk1:T --&amp;gt; B:server
    disk2:T -- B:db
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;block-beta

in space llm:2 space out
in[&amp;#34;Prompt&amp;#34;] --&amp;gt; llm[&amp;#34;Large Language Model&amp;#34;]
llm--&amp;gt; out[&amp;#34;Completion&amp;#34;]

style in fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
style out fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
   
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
