<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Peter&#39;s Griddle on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peter&#39;s Griddle on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.6</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:37:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Zero Trust Myths</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/zt-myths/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:37:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/zt-myths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the problem with the image that Zero Trust based information security brings along?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you understand the principles, and they are not really difficult, it is obvious that only ZT can lead us to a more secure cyber future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is holding us back?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the misconceptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It is a boatload of work, so let&amp;rsquo;s not start.&amp;rdquo; Truth: yes, fully securing your IT with all its technical debt is a boatload of work. That is exactly the reason why you need ZT, so that you know where you can get started quickly, and be more secure &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the last hole is plugged.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The AI Coding Age</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-coding-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 13:13:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-coding-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the dawn of a new age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been observing software development for more than fifty years, ever since I wrote my first computer program.
In that entire time, I have never witnessed a development that has changed the profession deeper, faster, or more pervasively than now.
AI-assisted coding has escaped from the lab, and is impacting the work of every software developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the communities I track I hear stories of software engineers regret taking a single week of vacation because of the innovations that they now have to catch up to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI will replace coders, not software engineers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-code-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 12:45:13 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-code-software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A coder in the world of IT is somebody who writes code in some programming language.
More typically they modify code instead of writing it from scratch.
This is in response to bugs, feature requests, and so on.
In the age of AI, a lot of coding can be automated.
While senior people often also code, not all coders are senior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A software engineer builds systems out of software.
This may involve coding, but there are many other ways to create business value with software.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibe OPSing with MCP: proof of concept</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-opsing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 09:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-opsing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the story of how I started to use AI to help with running and securing my home network.
I call it vibe ops, in analogy to vibe programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is going to be obsolete very soon, even though it is already the second version &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My home network plays an additional role as a nice lab, and in the process of better securing it, preferably with Zero Trust Architectures, I am doing some experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three books on Zero Trust, and when you should read them</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/three-books-zero-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 12:46:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/three-books-zero-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;But where do we start?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question hung in the air of my training session, asked by many of the attendants. Mind you, these are experienced people with many years of cyber security experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But turning Zero Trust from an abstract concept into concrete action? That&amp;rsquo;s where everyone gets stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that feeling well. Years ago, I joined my first Zero Trust working group, swimming in a sea of frameworks, agency guidelines, and vendor whitepapers. I even had the privilege of attending sessions with John Kindervag, the father of Zero Trust himself. Yet the gap between theory and implementation remained stubbornly wide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Saas Security: a Simple Checklist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/saas-security-simple-checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 10:56:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/saas-security-simple-checklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The security of your SaaS cloud solutions starts with the review of three major areas. Practically all companies are using SaaS providers in one way or another.
SaaS includes Services such as Trello for project management, Microsoft 365, and e.g. specialized solutions for marketing intelligence services. The sky is the limit. Most companies using are using hundreds of SaaS solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are 3 tips to start with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maturity-match&#34;&gt;Maturity match&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to worry about is if the maturity of the provider matches your risk appetite. Are they good enough for your use case?
If you are working with a mission-critical SaaS solution, you want to make sure that the provider is mature. You can start finding out if that is the case is by looking at their certifications. An example could be the ISO 27000 series certification for IT risk management, or similar. Most mature cloud providers have dozens of certifications. On the other end of the spectrum, you may want to work with a provider that is not so mature, but that is delivering a very innovative solution of great business benefit to your company. That benefit, that competitive edge, may warrant a greater risk appetite.
So start with that maturity match first.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great Introduction to Zero Trust</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/great-introduction-to-zero-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 10:48:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/great-introduction-to-zero-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Project Zero Trust” is a business novel by George Finney. It talks about an emerging approach to IT and Cybersecurity that attempts to reduce cyberrisk in a more fundamental way.
Zero Trust is a bit of a hype in IT these days, and both product companies and knowledge agencies are dropping lots of papers on this. But this book is in another game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I like about it is that it paints a reasonably realistic picture of a modern enterprise, including the information technology choices that it makes. This serves as a good backdrop to a variety of Zero Trust initiatives, which are described in a bit of detail.
As an instructor I find that most of the vendor neutral training material out there lacks specific examples. This makes it hard for students to anchor the abstract concepts that they are fed to a realistic environment with some resemblance to their job situation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Key Knowledge Gaps in Cloud Security and How to Address Them</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/key-knowledge-gaps-in-cloud-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 07:41:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/key-knowledge-gaps-in-cloud-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What are the real challenges in cloud security these days? In my recent conversations with industry practitioners, one came up consistently: the lack of knowledge and skills to adopt cloud securely.
These gaps are slowing down how teams build, manage and secure their cloud environments, and they may be affecting your teams as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;provider-specific-technical-expertise&#34;&gt;Provider specific technical expertise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many IT professionals attempt to transfer their on-premises security knowledge directly to cloud. But this often leads to ineffective and hard to maintain solutions.
A technical example is insisting on traditional firewall architectures. These are hard to implement right in the cloud and can lead to less secure deployments than are possible with cloud native architectures.
One set of skills that is relevant to addressing this is understanding what features a specific cloud provider has for building a secure architecture. There are many courses available from the providers, even free ones, though it can sometimes be a bit challenging to select the correct ones.
However, without understanding how abstraction and automation change the IT security game, these technical skills will not result in more efficiency. And without more efficiency security efforts will be outpaced by the speed of new developments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibe coding an MCP Server</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-mcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 08:39:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-mcp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Model Context Protocols (MCP, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/mcp-risk/&#34;&gt;my post on their security&lt;/a&gt;) are the new glue between humans, chatbots, and old school IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the step by step approach that I followed to &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-coding-real/&#34;&gt;vibe code&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; a Model Context Protocol server for my CRM and mailing list manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I journaled this description, so I have included most of the detours and false starts.
For readability, I edited the description later, but the flow is as I went through it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Look at MCP now to be ahead of AI risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mcp-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 06:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mcp-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are in security and not fully on top of AI risk, you want to look at MCP &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt;, as this is going to be popular and risky.
Reach out to your development teams and beyond to offer your help in using them wisely, even if you know nothing about them yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP, Model Context Protocol, was introduced in November 2024 as a standardised way to feed AI chatbots with extra information.
You can extend Claude or OpenAI desktop with MCP servers, which are basically small programs that run on the desktop and have access to all information and services that the user has.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Voice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-voice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:32:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-voice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;architecture-beta
    group frontend(cloud)[Frontend]
        service telco(cloud)[Telco] in frontend
        service sips(internet)[Sips] in frontend
    
    group backend(cloud)[Backend]
        service app_server(server)[Azure voice bot] in backend
        service twilio(internet)[Twilio] in backend
        service database(database)[Database] in backend
        service llm(server)[LLM] in backend


    group configuration(cloud)[Configuration]
        service faq(database)[FAQ mgt]    in configuration
    
    telco:R -- L:sips
    sips:R -- L:twilio
    twilio:R -- L:app_server
    app_server:B -- T:database
    llm:B -- T:app_server
    faq:R -- L:database
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibe Coding in Reality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-coding-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 14:34:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-coding-real/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How does vibe coding work in the real? Vibe coding is having AI write your software. Coined by Andrej Karpathy, the hype is all over the map, with companies that are rethinking their hiring strategies for programmers. Sounds like disaster for software engineers and programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not so fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curious to learn more about it, I reached out to an old friend who is an experienced software engineer. He was a co-founder in a SaaS company in the monitoring space. After a successful exit he now has a bit more time to pursue hobbies. But he is still professionally busy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Example Mermaid Client-Server</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/example-mermaid-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 11:21:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/example-mermaid-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;architecture-beta
    group frontend(cloud)[Frontend]
        service client(internet)[Client Browser] in frontend
    
    group backend(cloud)[Backend]
        service app_server(server)[Application Server] in backend
        service database(database)[Database] in backend
    
    client:B -- L:app_server
    app_server:B -- T:database
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big tech afhankelijkheid: wat is het echte risico?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/autonomie-van-bigtech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 09:36:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/autonomie-van-bigtech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Het nationale sentiment is negatief over de afhankelijkheid van &amp;lsquo;big tech&amp;rsquo;. Overheidsdata staat in een Amerikaanse cloud, we hebben geen eigen sociaal netwerk, enzovoort. En vergelijkbare sentimenten spelen bij andere organisaties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terecht wordt daarom nu op overheidsniveau een initiatief in gang gezet om wat aan die afhankelijkheid te doen. Dit initiatief staat ook bekend als &lt;a href=&#34;https://berthub.eu/articles/posts/cloud-kootwijk-moties-aangenomen/&#34;&gt;Cloud Kootwijk&lt;/a&gt;. Maar met een motie in de Kamer zijn we er nog niet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emoties zijn vaak een goede indicator, maar geen goede inhoudelijke analyse.
Ze leiden daarom nog wel eens tot beslissingen die onhandig, of zelfs contraproductief uitpakken. Hier legt de emotie wantrouwen bloot, maar waar die zich op richt moet een analyse uitwijzen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Elements of Cloud Security</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 22:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;five-elements-of-cloud-security&#34;&gt;Five elements of cloud security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, IT security started with &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure security&lt;/strong&gt;. Just protecting the data center was good enough. But that was before we had data communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When data started to escape the confines of the data center we needed to protect it. Typically through encryption. Hence we need &lt;strong&gt;data security&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the world wide web developed, we saw applications being exposed to it, and frankly, be vulnerable. So that is when &lt;strong&gt;application security&lt;/strong&gt; started to become more important.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How AI Can Help IT Risk Classification</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 19:45:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How cool would it be to let an AI do some of the grunt work in analysing the risk of applications and services. This has the potential to speed up the work of risk assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, does it work in practice? Well, here is an example of AI-assisted risk classification. I downloaded some of the entries in the Dutch &lt;a href=&#34;https://algoritmes.overheid.nl/en&#34;&gt;algorithm register&lt;/a&gt;, which is a public register of systems that use algorithms. For each entry about 30 fields are available, including name, classification, owner, et cetera.
Some of the systems in the registry are AI-based. Indeed, we have AI to help check on AI&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The US Air Force Zero Trust Strategy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 12:26:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Who is really doing Zero Trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the US Air Force is. Here is my summary, with some comments, of their strategy document for the benefit of my Certificate of Competence in Zero Trust (CCZT) learners. In fact, this is an edited version of a conversation we had during one of our classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the full strategy &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20API%20Reference%20Architecture%202.0.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the current roadmap &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20Enterprise%20Zero%20Trust%20Roadmap%20and%20Release%20Notes_v2.0.pdf?ver=36cbAKNEe7JiRVAPFwWepg%3d%3d&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, all linked from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the fundamental first important point about the strategy document is that it exists at all. There is an actual organization of significant size that has a strategy and is implementing it. Many can learn from this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Infrastructures - the graphic novel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 14:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the draft design of the graphic novel version of this book, which may or may not happen..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;digital world cyberpunk&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/dig-inf-front-page1.png&#34; title=&#34;With a little help from Dall-e&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can We Achieve Autonomy Over Our Digital Infrastructures?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 22:04:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-our-own-cloud-kootwijk-rethinking-digital-sovereignty&#34;&gt;Building Our Own Cloud Kootwijk: Rethinking Digital Sovereignty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, we are currently engaged in a heated debate about the undesirable dominance of big tech, particularly over a significant portion of the digital infrastructure of the Dutch government. This includes email, file storage, and many other forms of digital storage and processing—most of which are handled by American big tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure a similar debate is going on in many other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mermaid diagram example</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 09:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A diagram should automagically appear here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;sequenceDiagram
    actor Client
    actor Provider
    Client-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Provider: Query
    Note right of Provider: Please promise me to bring a drink
    Provider-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Client: Ack
    Note right of Provider: I promise to bring you a drink in a short while
    Provider-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Client: Reply
    Note right of Provider: Please promise me that you are satisfied and will pay
    Client-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Provider: Ack
    Note right of Provider: I promise to pay you for the drink
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;%%  icons from https://iconify.design
architecture-beta
    group api(Storage)[API]

    service db(database)[Database] in api
    service disk1(disk)[Storage] in api
    service disk2(disk)[Storage] in api
    service server(server)[Server] in api

    db:L -- R:server
    disk1:T --&amp;gt; B:server
    disk2:T -- B:db
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;block-beta

in space llm:2 space out
in[&amp;#34;Prompt&amp;#34;] --&amp;gt; llm[&amp;#34;Large Language Model&amp;#34;]
llm--&amp;gt; out[&amp;#34;Completion&amp;#34;]

style in fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
style out fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
   
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deployment diagrams for network security; fix this</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-diagram-fix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 17:09:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-diagram-fix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while back, I introduced my take on deployment diagrams for cloud and devops infrastructure. Some of the big points there are: it starts with intuitive drawings. Many people draw these things in similar ways, even without them having formal training.
In fact, formal training in architecture diagrams will not necessarily make those drawings easier to understand for the uninitiated.
But still. There are good drawings and there are drawings that can be improved.
My other big point is that deployment diagrams can be a great tool for security analysis. I am in some conversations with friends at banks who use them.
Recently I ran into the following example. Here is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://syang.substack.com/p/security-group-and-network-acl-in&#34;&gt;explanation of the difference between VPC and security groups&lt;/a&gt;. Great story, but I have some comments on the diagram, which used to come &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/vpc/latest/userguide/VPC_Security.html&#34;&gt;from AWS itself&lt;/a&gt;, by the way, but has been removed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top 8 cloud risks according to ENISA</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-8-cloud-risks-according-to-enisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 09:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-8-cloud-risks-according-to-enisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does security in the cloud ever bother you? It would be weird if it didn’t. Cloud computing has a lot of benefits, but also a lot of risks if done in the wrong way.
So what are the most important risks? The European Network Information Security Agency did extensive research on that in 2009 already, and identified 35 risk categories. This analysis is used by a number of players in the industry, including certain banking regulators. From those 35, ENISA has selected 8 as the most relevant ones. This article explains them, not in any particular order. (And by the way: ENISA is pronounced as ‘eniesa’, not ‘enaiza’).
You can also get the story on my YouTube video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directories are also infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/directories-are-also-infrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2006 10:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/directories-are-also-infrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the big projects I am working on right now (2006) is directory services for identity management. In these directories digital identities such as loginnames, addresses, access rights, etc. are stored. With an adequately structured directory service, the proper management of access rights becomes a lot easier, which translates into cost savings and better security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of these include the internet&amp;rsquo;s Domain Name System (DNS) and Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Active Directory. A lot of organizations however, have requirements beyond these systems, and for these a wide range of custom solutions are used.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Neutrality: who pays the ferryman?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-neutrality-who-pays-the-ferryman/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2006 13:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-neutrality-who-pays-the-ferryman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Network neutrality has become the topic of intense discussion and legislative action.&lt;br&gt;
See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/01/21/AR2006012100094.html&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; , a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_neutrality&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circleid.com/posts/network_neutrality/&#34;&gt;CircelID&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the issue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand people argue for &amp;lsquo;universal service&amp;rsquo; that say that one person&amp;rsquo;s bits should not be treated differently from another person&amp;rsquo;s. This compares to the idea that the phone company should not be allowed to treat your calls differently depending on what you want to say, or that red haired people would have a different monthly fee. There are laws against this type of discrimination (at least in most nations), and some people want to extend this law to Internet traffic. On the other hand there are some Internet providers who want to charge different customers different rates for different service. &amp;ldquo;We can&amp;rsquo;t have companies freeloading on our expensive pipes&amp;rdquo;, they claim.
Clearly we seem to want both. We don&amp;rsquo;t want the phone companies to decide which traffic gets carried, and we also don’t want a bland one-size-fits-all service that is expensive for some and inadequate for others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
