<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Diginf Scales on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Diginf Scales on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 15:35:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk is the flip side of value. For everything that is of value, there can be circumstances endangering that value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk in a digital world is not always easy to think through. While we can borrow a lot from the real world, certain important differences exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of every risk assessment there is the thing we worry about the most: the &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a digital world, this is often the &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of business critical data, like our database of customers. Think data that we have a compliance obligation on, such as personal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elements of the Digital World</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/elements-of-digitalinfrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 20:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/elements-of-digitalinfrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It all starts with bits: digital units of information. It is about how we store these bits, how we move these bits, and how we transform or process these bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three major elements of digital infrastructures are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the cloud security world, it is customary to talk about data at rest, data in motion, and data in use. This introduces data as the key common element. But more on cloud security later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provider Value</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/intro-to-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 09:10:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/intro-to-value/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The sheer separation of the providers from the consumers of these infrastructures drives a lot of the value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine stringing a wire to connect your PC to your neighbour&amp;rsquo;s PC in order to play a game together. People have been doing these things. How long does that take? What is the cost? Where do you buy the cable? How are you going to run that cable? It is a lot faster to just use the internet for that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Essence of Digital Infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/essence-digital-infrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 21:34:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/essence-digital-infrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What do roads, airports, the internet, the electricity network, and a search engine have in common? They are all services that are independent of a specific user or usage. They are provisioned on a longer timescale than that of an individual usage. And they are typically not owned by their users, or at least, not directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book I am mostly concerned with digital infrastructures. Their services are digitally accessible. Of the above examples, the internet and the search engine are the best examples of that. Interestingly, the other services increasingly rely on digital infrastructures themselves, or even incorporate specific digital infrastructures. An example of that are the trading platforms that enable the planning of electricity supply and demand. In many countries, electricity is a market, not a monopoly, which requires coordination between the various players.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Value in Process Improvement</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/value-in-process-improvement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 20:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/value-in-process-improvement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most digital infrastructures are meant to communicate or coordinate, or are in support of other digital infrastructures that communicate or coordinate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet is a prime example. It is designed to enable computers to communicate by moving data packets between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is another example, used by people to communicate with each other. Its success is a testament to the fact that communication is a fundamental human need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example of a supporting digital infrastructure you can look at an IaaS provider, which enables data processing and storage for other applications and infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What a lunch in Spain taught me about digital infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/lunch-spain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 16:06:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/lunch-spain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I visited my father in France. It turned out to be convenient to pick me up from the Gerona airport in Spain.
And as we had enough time, we had lunch in La Jonquera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the restaurant&amp;rsquo;s checkout I noticed a peculiar array of devices: there were four payment terminals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;payment terminals&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/payterminal-716603.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never seen that. From what I know, a merchant works with a bank which handles all their payments. Apparentely not over here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deployment Diagrams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/deployment-diagrams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 21:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/deployment-diagrams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deployment is everything that happens between writing software and actually using that software by its intended users. And as we get more software and more users, deployment becomes more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-deployment-diagrams&#34;&gt;Why deployment diagrams?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment diagrams are a great technique for communicating about important decisions in deploying software. Decisions such as who is going to do what, how are things connected, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to draw deployment diagrams and many standards to choose from. UML and Archimate are just a few of them. To me, there is no single right way to create deployment diagrams. In that sense, these diagrams are more like maps. And the usefulness of a map depends on the journey that you are going to make. A map for a mountain walk is pretty useless if you want to make a railroad journey and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Requires Cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/agile-requires-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 15:12:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/agile-requires-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile development&lt;/strong&gt; is all the fashion nowadays. Why is that and what kind of digital infrastructures does that require?
Back in the old days, business software was primarily written to automate &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; business processes. Those processes might change somewhat as a result, but in the core processes were no different. Think accounting systems, scheduling, &amp;ldquo;customer relationship management&amp;rdquo; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we see that software not only automates these business processes, but becomes part of the product, or even becomes the product itself. And on top of that, this software is often an on-line service. Think of the smart room thermostat. Or financial services, where software increasingly is the main part of the product: think online banking. And in social media from Facebook to Tindr, software really is the product.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Business Model Canvas for IaaS Providers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-iaas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2014 11:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-iaas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;business-model-canvas&#34;&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business model canvas is a visual template for developing and discussing business models. For more information, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_Model_Canvas&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_Model_Canvas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessmodelgeneration.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.businessmodelgeneration.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business model canvas has nine basic building blocks and specific relations between those blocks. I&amp;rsquo;ll illustrate them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example used in this section is Amazon Web Services (AWS), particularly EC2 (virtual machines on demand). This is an Infrastructure as a Service offering. The power of the business model canvas approach becomes clear when we see how it can distinguish between various cloud service offerings.
&lt;img alt=&#34;IaaS Cloud Canvas&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-iaas/BusinessCanvasIaaS.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Business Model Canvas for SaaS Providers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-saas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 11:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-saas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a high level overview of the SaaS provider business model and some of the strategic options that are in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;business-model-canvas&#34;&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Business Model Canvas is a strategic management tool that serves as a visual framework for developing and discussing business models. To learn more, visit &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_Model_Canvas&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessmodelgeneration.com/&#34;&gt;Business Model Generation&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Business Model Canvas is composed of nine essential building blocks, which define the interconnections and relationships within a business model. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore examples using two hypothetical SaaS providers: one offering bookkeeping software and the other a project collaboration platform.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Ways to Go Cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/three-ways-to-go-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 17:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/three-ways-to-go-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Public cloud migrations come in different shapes and sizes, but I see three major approaches. Each of these has very different technical and governance implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-approaches&#34;&gt;Three approaches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies dying to get rid of their data centers often get started on a &lt;strong&gt;‘lift and shift’&lt;/strong&gt; approach, where applications are moved from existing servers to equivalent servers in the cloud. The cloud service model consumed here is mainly IaaS (infrastructure as a service). Not much is outsourced to cloud providers here. Contrast that with SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How My Site Got Hacked</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/how-my-site-got-hacked/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 15:35:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/how-my-site-got-hacked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;detection&#34;&gt;Detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have acted on the first signals more aggressively. But let’s talk about that later in this story.
Here is the story of my site being infected with malware, viewed by a professional cloud security expert. So I am going to apply all that cloud security theory to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hack led to business damage at the end of one of my webinars. In 2016, on a Friday, I did a webinar, at the end of which I had two links to my site as a call to action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Elements of Cloud Security</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 22:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;five-elements-of-cloud-security&#34;&gt;Five elements of cloud security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, IT security started with &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure security&lt;/strong&gt;. Just protecting the data center was good enough. But that was before we had data communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When data started to escape the confines of the data center we needed to protect it. Typically through encryption. Hence we need &lt;strong&gt;data security&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the world wide web developed, we saw applications being exposed to it, and frankly, be vulnerable. So that is when &lt;strong&gt;application security&lt;/strong&gt; started to become more important.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How AI Can Help IT Risk Classification</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 19:45:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How cool would it be to let an AI do some of the grunt work in analysing the risk of applications and services. This has the potential to speed up the work of risk assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, does it work in practice? Well, here is an example of AI-assisted risk classification. I downloaded some of the entries in the Dutch &lt;a href=&#34;https://algoritmes.overheid.nl/en&#34;&gt;algorithm register&lt;/a&gt;, which is a public register of systems that use algorithms. For each entry about 30 fields are available, including name, classification, owner, et cetera.
Some of the systems in the registry are AI-based. Indeed, we have AI to help check on AI&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying technology by following a system</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/technical-meta-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/technical-meta-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How to fix the WiFi? How to find a new phone for grandma?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying technology follows certain rules. However, many people only have an intuitive understanding of these rules. As a result technology is not optimally applied.
By understanding how applying technology really works, you can be more effective, more efficient, reduce waste, and overall do a better job. It takes just a few simple steps to improve any attempt at applying technology. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on information technology here, though most principles have wider applicability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Actors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/international-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/international-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The international arena has many actors that can influence digital infrastructures. But opinions differ on what the important ones are, or even what the relevant ones are.
By the nature of scaling, very few digital infrastructures are influenced by national actors only. The international arena is complex, and there are even conflicting views on how it is made up.
These conflicting views can best be seen as maps of the territory. And as I have mentioned earlier, a map is only relevant for a specific purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The US Air Force Zero Trust Strategy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 12:26:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Who is really doing Zero Trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the US Air Force is. Here is my summary, with some comments, of their strategy document for the benefit of my Certificate of Competence in Zero Trust (CCZT) learners. In fact, this is an edited version of a conversation we had during one of our classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the full strategy &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20API%20Reference%20Architecture%202.0.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the current roadmap &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20Enterprise%20Zero%20Trust%20Roadmap%20and%20Release%20Notes_v2.0.pdf?ver=36cbAKNEe7JiRVAPFwWepg%3d%3d&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, all linked from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the fundamental first important point about the strategy document is that it exists at all. There is an actual organization of significant size that has a strategy and is implementing it. Many can learn from this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snippets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/snippets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 12:05:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/snippets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk: LMS 3-2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CERN data center&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;verhaal over corporate en MKB&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How technical debt works: negative investment externalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course you have this discussion on shared services. As a matter of fact, I keep talking about the book that I&amp;rsquo;m probably not going to finish, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a nice frame of reference. Now digital infrastructures at scale - there are a few very essential elements in there. The most important elements are: one, that you have a separation between a provider and multiple consumers; and two, that that service is digital, which means that it&amp;rsquo;s amenable to automation. These two together give a really interesting socio-political economic dynamic. And that&amp;rsquo;s what you need to understand if you want your shared service to keep operating - or if you don&amp;rsquo;t want it to operate, but that&amp;rsquo;s a different story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Requires Cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/agile-requires-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 21:15:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/agile-requires-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile development&lt;/strong&gt; is all the fashion nowadays. Why is that and what kind of digital infrastructures does that require?
Back in the old days, business software was primarily written to automate &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; business processes. Those processes might change somewhat as a result, but in the core processes were no different. Think accounting systems, scheduling, &amp;ldquo;customer relationship management&amp;rdquo; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we see that software not only automates these business processes, but becomes part of the product, or even becomes the product itself. And on top of that, this software is often an on-line service. Think of the smart room thermostat. Or financial services, where software increasingly is the main part of the product: think online banking. And in social media from Facebook to Tindr, software really is the product.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Infrastructures - the graphic novel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 14:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the draft design of the graphic novel version of this book, which may or may not happen..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;digital world cyberpunk&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/dig-inf-front-page1.png&#34; title=&#34;With a little help from Dall-e&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positions of Power in IT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 11:06:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspirations of Digital Infrastructures at Scale is to equip you with the tools to shape and drive change in your professional environment—especially when your goal is to lead a transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important positions of influence in IT are architects and auditors/assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IT architects are builders. They design new applications, platforms, and infrastructures that enable businesses to operate more effectively. A CRM system, for example, is not just a technical solution—it transforms workflows, communication, and decision-making. Similarly, infrastructure architects create digital foundations that accelerate the deployment of such applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are AI digital infrastructures?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/digital-inf-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2025 17:57:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/digital-inf-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The AI landscape has many digital infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s explain this step by step and focus on which data is stored where, and how it is processed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A core element of AI systems is a trained model. At least that is true for the dominant AI form these days: deep learning neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trained model is the result of processing a lot of training data by a specific neural network. These models are fixed in size, but typically very big. The smallest useful models are close to a Gigabyte, while recent public chat models run into multiple Terabytes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can We Achieve Autonomy Over Our Digital Infrastructures?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 22:04:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-our-own-cloud-kootwijk-rethinking-digital-sovereignty&#34;&gt;Building Our Own Cloud Kootwijk: Rethinking Digital Sovereignty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, we are currently engaged in a heated debate about the undesirable dominance of big tech, particularly over a significant portion of the digital infrastructure of the Dutch government. This includes email, file storage, and many other forms of digital storage and processing—most of which are handled by American big tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure a similar debate is going on in many other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preface</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/preface/preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 22:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/preface/preface/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book has been more than thirty years in the making.
The two main reasons for that, as I look back on that now, are that the field of Information Technology has been developing incredibly rapidly, and that I did not see the opportunity within my business to create a focus for which writing a book would make business sense. And if I did, the focus never seemed to last very long.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrofitting Zero Trust on an existing application: an illustration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 14:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Architecture is an approach to better cybersecurity. To many, it seems daunting to implement. But it does not have to be hard to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this hypothetical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an application with hundreds of thousands of sensitive records, let’s say client records. We assume that in this example it seems hard to implement MFA (Multi Factor Authentication) on it. What other controls can you implement to reduce the assumed trust? We can use the Kipling method, which is at the core of Zero Trust architectures, to engineer better controls. In short, the Kipling method is about the &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo;, etcetera of allowed communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mermaid diagram example</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 09:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A diagram should automagically appear here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;%%  icons from https://iconify.design
architecture-beta
    group api(Storage)[API]

    service db(database)[Database] in api
    service disk1(disk)[Storage] in api
    service disk2(disk)[Storage] in api
    service server(server)[Server] in api

    db:L -- R:server
    disk1:T --&amp;gt; B:server
    disk2:T -- B:db
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;block-beta

in space llm:2 space out
in[&amp;#34;Prompt&amp;#34;] --&amp;gt; llm[&amp;#34;Large Language Model&amp;#34;]
llm--&amp;gt; out[&amp;#34;Completion&amp;#34;]

style in fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
style out fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
   
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deployment diagrams for network security; fix this</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-diagram-fix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 17:09:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-diagram-fix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while back, I introduced my take on deployment diagrams for cloud and devops infrastructure. Some of the big points there are: it starts with intuitive drawings. Many people draw these things in similar ways, even without them having formal training.
In fact, formal training in architecture diagrams will not necessarily make those drawings easier to understand for the uninitiated.
But still. There are good drawings and there are drawings that can be improved.
My other big point is that deployment diagrams can be a great tool for security analysis. I am in some conversations with friends at banks who use them.
Recently I ran into the following example. Here is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://syang.substack.com/p/security-group-and-network-acl-in&#34;&gt;explanation of the difference between VPC and security groups&lt;/a&gt;. Great story, but I have some comments on the diagram, which happens to come &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/vpc/latest/userguide/VPC_Security.html&#34;&gt;from AWS itself&lt;/a&gt;, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top 8 cloud risks according to ENISA</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-8-cloud-risks-according-to-enisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 09:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-8-cloud-risks-according-to-enisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does security in the cloud ever bother you? It would be weird if it didn’t. Cloud computing has a lot of benefits, but also a lot of risks if done in the wrong way.
So what are the most important risks? The European Network Information Security Agency did extensive research on that in 2009 already, and identified 35 risk categories. This analysis is used by a number of players in the industry, including certain banking regulators. From those 35, ENISA has selected 8 as the most relevant ones. This article explains them, not in any particular order. (And by the way: ENISA is pronounced as ‘eniesa’, not ‘enaiza’).
You can also get the story on my YouTube video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directories are also infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/directories-are-also-infrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2006 10:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/directories-are-also-infrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the big projects I am working on right now (2006) is directory services for identity management. In these directories digital identities such as loginnames, addresses, access rights, etc. are stored. With an adequately structured directory service, the proper management of access rights becomes a lot easier, which translates into cost savings and better security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of these include the internet&amp;rsquo;s Domain Name System (DNS) and Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Active Directory. A lot of organizations however, have requirements beyond these systems, and for these a wide range of custom solutions are used.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
