<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Diginf Scales on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Diginf Scales on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 21:05:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 13:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/intro-to-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Risk is the flip side of value. For everything that is of value, there can be circumstances threatening that value.
While value is realized in the past and the present, risk is what can happen with that value in the &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk in a digital world is not always easy to think through. While we can borrow a lot from the real world, certain important differences exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of every risk assessment there is the thing we worry about the most: the &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;asset&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo;.
In a digital world, this is often the &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Think of business critical data, like our database of customers. Think data that we have a compliance obligation on, such as personal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elements of the Digital World</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/elements-of-digitalinfrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 20:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/elements-of-digitalinfrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It all starts with bits: digital units of information. It is about how we store these bits, how we move these bits, and how we transform or process these bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three major elements of digital infrastructures are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the cloud security world, it is customary to talk about data at rest, data in motion, and data in use. This introduces data as the key common element. But more on cloud security later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A brief history of LLM tooling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/brief-llm-tool/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 14:57:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/brief-llm-tool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In order to illustrate the development of technology through tracking the development of LLM related tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2023 (check) ChatGPT came out.
Within days people from around the world were using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAG - companies
Langchain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP and A2A&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP spinoffs&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why You Should Read</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/why-you-should-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 08:47:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/why-you-should-read/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You should not read this book because I tell you to.
After all, you are an autonomous person, making your own decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should read this book because you are convinced that it is likely to give you significant insights into a world that matters to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital infrastructures, and information technology at large, have moved from a fringe niche technology to becoming an essential part of modern life.
Most companies would go belly up in weeks, if not days, if their digital infrastructures would fail.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the value of information?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/value-of-information/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 11:33:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/value-of-information/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is information really?
If we know that, we can try to understand how we can judge its value, or even start to understand how we can create value with information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Claude Shannon&amp;rsquo;s theory of communication, information is about reducing uncertainty.
Another way is to say that more information means less noise because if you add noise to information, that information will have more uncertainty and less value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To visualise this, think of a picture that is obscured by a bit of fog or haze.
You can still see some of the picture, but not very clearly.
You will make more errors when trying to understand what the picture means.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three books on Zero Trust, and when you should read them</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/three-books-zero-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 12:46:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/three-books-zero-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;But where do we start?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question hung in the air of my training session, asked by many of the attendants. Mind you, these are experienced people with many years of cyber security experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But turning Zero Trust from an abstract concept into concrete action? That&amp;rsquo;s where everyone gets stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that feeling well. Years ago, I joined my first Zero Trust working group, swimming in a sea of frameworks, agency guidelines, and vendor whitepapers. I even had the privilege of attending sessions with John Kindervag, the father of Zero Trust himself. Yet the gap between theory and implementation remained stubbornly wide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Saas Security: a Simple Checklist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/saas-security-simple-checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 10:56:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/saas-security-simple-checklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The security of your SaaS cloud solutions starts with the review of three major areas. Practically all companies are using SaaS providers in one way or another.
SaaS includes Services such as Trello for project management, Microsoft 365, and e.g. specialized solutions for marketing intelligence services. The sky is the limit. Most companies using are using hundreds of SaaS solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are 3 tips to start with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maturity-match&#34;&gt;Maturity match&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to worry about is if the maturity of the provider matches your risk appetite. Are they good enough for your use case?
If you are working with a mission-critical SaaS solution, you want to make sure that the provider is mature. You can start finding out if that is the case is by looking at their certifications. An example could be the ISO 27000 series certification for IT risk management, or similar. Most mature cloud providers have dozens of certifications. On the other end of the spectrum, you may want to work with a provider that is not so mature, but that is delivering a very innovative solution of great business benefit to your company. That benefit, that competitive edge, may warrant a greater risk appetite.
So start with that maturity match first.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great Introduction to Zero Trust</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/great-introduction-to-zero-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 10:48:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/great-introduction-to-zero-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Project Zero Trust” is a business novel by George Finney. It talks about an emerging approach to IT and Cybersecurity that attempts to reduce cyberrisk in a more fundamental way.
Zero Trust is a bit of a hype in IT these days, and both product companies and knowledge agencies are dropping lots of papers on this. But this book is in another game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I like about it is that it paints a reasonably realistic picture of a modern enterprise, including the information technology choices that it makes. This serves as a good backdrop to a variety of Zero Trust initiatives, which are described in a bit of detail.
As an instructor I find that most of the vendor neutral training material out there lacks specific examples. This makes it hard for students to anchor the abstract concepts that they are fed to a realistic environment with some resemblance to their job situation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Key Knowledge Gaps in Cloud Security and How to Address Them</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/key-knowledge-gaps-in-cloud-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 07:41:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/key-knowledge-gaps-in-cloud-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What are the real challenges in cloud security these days? In my recent conversations with industry practitioners, one came up consistently: the lack of knowledge and skills to adopt cloud securely.
These gaps are slowing down how teams build, manage and secure their cloud environments, and they may be affecting your teams as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;provider-specific-technical-expertise&#34;&gt;Provider specific technical expertise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many IT professionals attempt to transfer their on-premises security knowledge directly to cloud. But this often leads to ineffective and hard to maintain solutions.
A technical example is insisting on traditional firewall architectures. These are hard to implement right in the cloud and can lead to less secure deployments than are possible with cloud native architectures.
One set of skills that is relevant to addressing this is understanding what features a specific cloud provider has for building a secure architecture. There are many courses available from the providers, even free ones, though it can sometimes be a bit challenging to select the correct ones.
However, without understanding how abstraction and automation change the IT security game, these technical skills will not result in more efficiency. And without more efficiency security efforts will be outpaced by the speed of new developments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibe coding an MCP Server</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-mcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 08:39:55 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-mcp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Model Context Protocols (MCP, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/mcp-risk/&#34;&gt;my post on their security&lt;/a&gt;) are the new glue between humans, chatbots, and old school IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the step by step approach that I followed to &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-coding-real/&#34;&gt;vibe code&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; a Model Context Protocol server for my CRM and mailing list manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I journaled this description, so I have included most of the detours and false starts.
For readability, I edited the description later, but the flow is as I went through it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promise Theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/promise-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 21:21:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/promise-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Digital infrastructures focus on services rather than products, making it elusive to capture the essence of these services, especially in defining the fluid interactions between service providers and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promise theory is a little-known approach to interaction, though it has quite a few great thinkers behind it.
Introduced by Mark Burgess and others, it is about how autonomous agents work together.
It helped me a lot in getting a handle on various distributed systems.
There was this project where we designed a scalable travel information system with what we now call microservices.
We needed to describe how these parts work together.
And there was a project that required lots of independent and autonomous social security agencies to work together on providing a service.
In getting this from the drawing board to actual production, promise theory turned out to be a great tool.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Look at MCP now to be ahead of AI risk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mcp-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 06:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mcp-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are in security and not fully on top of AI risk, you want to look at MCP &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt;, as this is going to be popular and risky.
Reach out to your development teams and beyond to offer your help in using them wisely, even if you know nothing about them yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP, Model Context Protocol, was introduced in November 2024 as a standardised way to feed AI chatbots with extra information.
You can extend Claude or OpenAI desktop with MCP servers, which are basically small programs that run on the desktop and have access to all information and services that the user has.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Voice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-voice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:32:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-voice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;architecture-beta
    group frontend(cloud)[Frontend]
        service telco(cloud)[Telco] in frontend
        service sips(internet)[Sips] in frontend
    
    group backend(cloud)[Backend]
        service app_server(server)[Azure voice bot] in backend
        service twilio(internet)[Twilio] in backend
        service database(database)[Database] in backend
        service llm(server)[LLM] in backend


    group configuration(cloud)[Configuration]
        service faq(database)[FAQ mgt]    in configuration
    
    telco:R -- L:sips
    sips:R -- L:twilio
    twilio:R -- L:app_server
    app_server:B -- T:database
    llm:B -- T:app_server
    faq:R -- L:database
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Things Break at Scale</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/things-break-at-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 21:16:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/things-break-at-scale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Computers are terribly reliable, in general. Today&amp;rsquo;s computer systems execute millions, even trillions, of instructions each second, with an error rate that is inconceivable in other technologies. Yet, if you have hundreds of thousands of machines, you do need to take care of failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days of Google growth I read an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnet.com/culture/google-spotlights-data-center-inner-workings/&#34;&gt;article about their error numbers&lt;/a&gt;
(a Google cluster has several thousands of machines):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each cluster&amp;rsquo;s first year, it&amp;rsquo;s typical that 1,000 individual machine failures will occur; thousands of hard drive failures will occur; one power distribution unit will fail, bringing down 500 to 1,000 machines for about 6 hours; 20 racks will fail, each time causing 40 to 80 machines to vanish from the network; 5 racks will &amp;ldquo;go wonky,&amp;rdquo; with half their network packets missing in action; and the cluster will have to be rewired once, affecting 5 percent of the machines at any given moment over a 2-day span, Dean said. And there&amp;rsquo;s about a 50 percent chance that the cluster will overheat, taking down most of the servers in less than 5 minutes and taking 1 to 2 days to recover.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applications</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 21:11:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An application is roughly a data model plus a certain number of functions operating on that.
Networked applications typically live on servers, but will have a client component.
A word processor is an application. Its data model is formatted text, and the functionality allows you to manipulate that text.
Another example would be gmail, whose data model is a set of messages, and the functionality allows you to manipulate the messages and their flow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Suffers?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/who-suffers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 21:27:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/who-suffers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have found that no discussion on risk is going to lead anywhere if it does not make clear who suffers from it.
Make clear who has the pain.
For my phone and laptop it is easy: if I lose them, I suffer.
In a larger organisation it is less clear.
Suppose a server dies.
Whose application then no longer runs?
Who has to pay for a new server?
This gets increasingly harder if we are talking about shared services, because the owner and the consumer are now decoupled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibe Coding in Reality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-coding-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 14:34:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/vibe-coding-real/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How does vibe coding work in the real? Vibe coding is having AI write your software. Coined by Andrej Karpathy, the hype is all over the map, with companies that are rethinking their hiring strategies for programmers. Sounds like disaster for software engineers and programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not so fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curious to learn more about it, I reached out to an old friend who is an experienced software engineer. He was a co-founder in a SaaS company in the monitoring space. After a successful exit he now has a bit more time to pursue hobbies. But he is still professionally busy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Change and Control</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/intro-to-change-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 09:17:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/intro-to-change-control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Change is quite inherent in technology, and in particular in information technology.
At the same time we want technology to provide a reliable service, and that requires a degree of control.
In this chapter we&amp;rsquo;ll explore some fundamentals of change, in particular how this works with groups of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change and control mindsets complement each other.
We need both, even if they conflict at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in a typical IT environment, you have developers and system administrators.
The output of the developers is a stream of changes: new features, improvements, bug fixes, and so on.
Adminstrators are in the business of keeping everything stable, the same.
They see no fundamental difference between a new feature and an incident. Both are disrupting the normal flow of business. Consequently, they are seen as a threat, and that is why it often feels that developers and system administrators are from different planets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Power</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/intro-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:31:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/intro-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Power is a concept that is widely used and ill defined. Many philosophers have discussed it, but not one definition really stands out.
Before we attempt to define power formally, let&amp;rsquo;s see how the word in used in everyday IT situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding power in IT is not just academic. As the examples show it is crucial in understanding how IT works, and creates value and risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cloud architect held significant power in deciding which platforms the organization would adopt for its digital transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated deployment pipelines gave development teams the power to release software faster and with fewer errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legacy systems often retain unexpected power in large organizations, simply because so many critical processes still depend on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regulators have the power to halt digital initiatives if data protection requirements are not met.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By owning the central identity management service, the security team had the power to control access across the entire infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outages at major cloud providers show how concentrated power in digital infrastructures can lead to systemic risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CIO used the power of budget approval to steer the enterprise toward adopting more secure infrastructure patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power struggles between central IT and business units can delay the rollout of shared infrastructure services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With real-time observability tools, operations teams gained the power to detect and respond to incidents before users were affected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open-source community can collectively wield more power than a single vendor when shaping the direction of a software tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these examples, we can see certain recurring features of power in the context of IT and digital infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Value in Process Improvement</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/value-in-process-improvement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 20:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/value-in-process-improvement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most digital infrastructures are meant to communicate or coordinate, or are in support of other digital infrastructures that communicate or coordinate.
That is where their prime value is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet is a great example. It is designed to enable computers to communicate by moving data packets between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is another example, used by people to communicate with each other. Its success is a testament to the fact that communication is a fundamental human need.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Essence of Digital Infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/essence-digital-infrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 21:34:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/essence-digital-infrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What do roads, airports, the internet, the electricity network, and a search engine have in common? They are all services that are independent of a specific user or usage. They are provisioned on a longer timescale than that of an individual usage. And they are typically not owned by their users, or at least, not directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book I am mostly concerned with digital infrastructures. Their services are digitally accessible. Of the above examples, the internet and the search engine are the best examples of that. Interestingly, the other services increasingly rely on digital infrastructures themselves, or even incorporate specific digital infrastructures. An example of that is the trading platforms that enable the planning of electricity supply and demand. In many countries, electricity is a market, not a monopoly, which requires coordination between the various players.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promise Theory Part2</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/promise-theory-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 15:30:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/promise-theory-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rooted in Deontic logic (obligations, commitments, permissions)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The moral necessity of talking about power</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/ethics-of-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 20:30:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/ethics-of-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For many people, the word power has a negative connotation.
They&amp;rsquo;d rather avoid using power altogether.
I can feel that, and I can definitely feel that about the abuse of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But does that make it unethical to talk about power?
Power is everywhere, and conflict too. There is no society without a power structure.
There are always differences of opinions in any group, if only to decide when to have lunch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control Through Feedback Loops</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/control-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 20:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/control-feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to influence and control a system, but one of the most controlled (pun intended) ways is to use feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with an analogy first: driving a car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want the car to stop as fast as possible, it suffices to push the brakes as hard as you can. But that does not give you much control.
For example, your passengers might not like it, and it leads to wear on the tires.
If you want the car to stop at an intended location, for example just in front of a traffic light, you apply a feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Security Assets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/assets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 08:37:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/assets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s dive a little deeper into assets, which is typically data that we have risks on, though we can also see the processing power that we need as an asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a risk analysis, the asset is the unit that we consider.
ENISA, the European Network Information Security Agency, is one of the many institutes in the world described IT risk management.
In a report on cloud security (reference) they identified a number of assets.
A few examples to illustrate the breadth of that are:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What about AI Risks?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/querying-ai-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 07:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/querying-ai-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While Artificial Intelligence, especially the generative type, is a highly disruptive form of IT innovation, its risk management still follows the same basic principles.
We just need to extend those principles to new forms of data and software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the assets?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the vulnerabilities and threats to it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the damage that this can bring, realistically?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s see how what the AI specifics are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ai-assets&#34;&gt;AI Assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s focus on the AI assets that are the product of deep learning.
Deep learning neural networks have represented a shift in AI technology.
Before that, symbolic AI was more common.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematically applying technology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/technical-meta-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/technical-meta-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How to fix the WiFi? How to find a new phone for grandma?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying technology follows certain rules. However, many people only have an intuitive understanding of these rules. As a result technology is not optimally applied.
By understanding how applying technology really works, you can be more effective, more efficient, reduce waste, and overall do a better job. It takes just a few simple steps to improve any attempt at applying technology. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on information technology here, though most principles have wider applicability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What a lunch in Spain taught me about digital infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/lunch-spain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 16:06:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/lunch-spain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I visited my father in France. It turned out to be convenient to pick me up from the Gerona airport in Spain.
And as we had enough time, we had lunch in La Jonquera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the restaurant&amp;rsquo;s checkout I noticed a peculiar array of devices: there were four payment terminals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;payment terminals&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/payterminal-716603.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never seen that. From what I know, a merchant works with a bank which handles all their payments. Apparently not over here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provider Value</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/intro-to-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 09:10:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/intro-to-value/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consumers of digital infrastructures benefit from not running them themselves, but having a provider who serves more consumers do it for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine stringing a wire to connect your PC to your neighbour&amp;rsquo;s PC in order to play a game together. People have been doing these things. How long does it take to string the wires and connect them? What is the cost? Where do you buy the cable? How are you going to run that cable? It is a lot faster to just use the internet for that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Governance over IT, an example</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/governance-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 11:07:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/governance-example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shared resources can lead to conflicts.
If the capacity runs out, somebody will feel the pain at the expense of somebody else.
This conflict will be resolved in one way or another.
Without other arrangements, the stakeholder with the most power wins.
This is not necessarily the best outcome for the organisation as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this, I gave ChatGPT the following prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a business case story about the conflict over shared computing resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Is Trust</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/what-is-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 10:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/what-is-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trust is an essential element in any collaboration.
We want to trust things, people, and organizations to do the right thing, to keep their promises.
Without trust, we will not be able to have confidence in the contribution of others, and that is a risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything we don&amp;rsquo;t trust is a risk.
Anytime we assume trust that is not warranted is also a risk.
That is one of the core concepts of Zero Trust Security Architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positions of Power in IT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 11:06:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspirations of Digital Infrastructures at Scale is to equip you with the tools to shape and drive change in your professional environment—especially when your goal is to lead a transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important positions of influence in IT are architects and auditors/assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IT architects are builders. They design new applications, platforms, and infrastructures that enable businesses to operate more effectively. A CRM system, for example, is not just a technical solution—it transforms workflows, communication, and decision-making. Similarly, infrastructure architects create digital foundations that accelerate the deployment of such applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power Flows</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/power-mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/power-mediation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Power does not automatically flow from those that have it to those that are influenced by it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they say in dutch, quoting the poet Willem Elsschot: &amp;ldquo;tussen droom en daad staan wetten in de weg, en praktische bezwaren&amp;rdquo;. (&amp;ldquo;between dream and deed stand laws in the way, and practical objections&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to understand this. If we want to exercise power, we need to understand the intermediaries. If we want to subvert power, the intermediaries are one of our disruptive points.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Execution Environments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/execution-environments/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/execution-environments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What do a laptop, a smartphone, and a smart thermostat have in common with a browser, a database, and a datacenter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are all execution environments that contain software and data, and that makes them building blocks for deploying digital infrastructures.
In a diagram we often depict them as a box, or an oval.
Inside the box, software gets executed, instructions get interpreted, actions are done. Software without execution is just dead data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Requires Cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/agile-requires-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 15:12:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/agile-requires-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile development&lt;/strong&gt; is all the fashion nowadays. Why is that and what kind of digital infrastructures does that require?
Back in the old days, business software was primarily written to automate &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; business processes. Those processes might change somewhat as a result, but in the core processes were no different. Think accounting systems, scheduling, &amp;ldquo;customer relationship management&amp;rdquo; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we see that software not only automates these business processes, but becomes part of the product, or even becomes the product itself. And on top of that, this software is often an on-line service. Think of the smart room thermostat.
Or financial services, where software increasingly is the main part of the product: think online banking. And in social media from Facebook to Tindr, software really is the product.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Management Automation - the DHCP case</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/dhcp-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 14:20:26 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/dhcp-automation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we mature processes, they come within reach of actual automation. Especially IT management processes. To paraphrase General Carl von Clausewitz, who said &amp;ldquo;War is the continuation of diplomacy with different means&amp;rdquo;, we can say that automation is the progression of process maturity with different means - replacing human effort with software and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite historical example is IP address allocation. In the past, whenever there was a new computer, you would walk up to the head of the lab or data center and ask for a new IP address for that machine. You may remember that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Business Model Canvas for IaaS Providers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-iaas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2014 11:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-iaas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;business-model-canvas&#34;&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business model canvas is a visual template for developing and discussing business models. For more information, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_Model_Canvas&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_Model_Canvas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessmodelgeneration.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.businessmodelgeneration.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business model canvas has nine basic building blocks and specific relations between those blocks. I&amp;rsquo;ll illustrate them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example used in this section is Amazon Web Services (AWS), particularly EC2 (virtual machines on demand). This is an Infrastructure as a Service offering. The power of the business model canvas approach becomes clear when we see how it can distinguish between various cloud service offerings.
&lt;img alt=&#34;IaaS Cloud Canvas&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-iaas/BusinessCanvasIaaS.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technology architecture for non-techies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/new-skills-needed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 08:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/new-skills-needed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the technical architecture of digital infrastructures is critically important, in particular for &lt;em&gt;non-technical&lt;/em&gt; professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have spent more than a decade educating people on cloud security, for example through certifications such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.clubcloudcomputing.com/ccsk/&#34;&gt;Certificate of Cloud Security Knowledge (CCSK)&lt;/a&gt;, organized by the Cloud Security Alliance (CSA), and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.clubcloudcomputing.com/ccsp/&#34;&gt;Certified Cloud Security Professional (CCSP)&lt;/a&gt;, as organized by (ISC)2.
These bodies of knowledge cover a lot of ground, and most of it is related to digital infrastructures at scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deployment Diagrams</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/deployment-diagrams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 21:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/deployment-diagrams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deployment is everything that happens between writing software and actually using that software by its intended users. And as we get more software and more users, deployment becomes more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-deployment-diagrams&#34;&gt;Why deployment diagrams?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment diagrams are a great technique for communicating about important decisions in deploying software. Decisions such as who is going to do what, how are things connected, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to draw deployment diagrams and many standards to choose from. UML and Archimate are just a few of them. To me, there is no single right way to create deployment diagrams. In that sense, these diagrams are more like maps. And the usefulness of a map depends on the journey that you are going to make. A map for a mountain walk is pretty useless if you want to make a railroad journey and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are AI digital infrastructures?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/digital-inf-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2025 17:57:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/digital-inf-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The AI landscape has many digital infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s explain this step by step and focus on which data is stored where, and how it is processed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A core element of AI systems is a trained model. At least that is true for the dominant AI form these days: deep learning neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trained model is the result of processing a lot of training data by a specific neural network. These models are fixed in size, but typically very big. The smallest useful models are close to a Gigabyte, while recent public chat models run into multiple Terabytes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Business Model Canvas for SaaS Providers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-saas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 11:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/business-model-canvas-saas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a high level overview of the SaaS provider business model and some of the strategic options that are in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;business-model-canvas&#34;&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Business Model Canvas is a strategic management tool that serves as a visual framework for developing and discussing business models. To learn more, visit &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Business_Model_Canvas&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessmodelgeneration.com/&#34;&gt;Business Model Generation&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Business Model Canvas is composed of nine essential building blocks, which define the interconnections and relationships within a business model. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore examples using two hypothetical SaaS providers: one offering bookkeeping software and the other a project collaboration platform.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who made podcasting big?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/the-tipping-point-for-podcasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2005 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/the-tipping-point-for-podcasting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Podcasting has its own digital infrastructures, for example in hosting them.
Let&amp;rsquo;s look at how podcasting has grown, and what made it take off anyway?
Many actors influence each other here, and the state of the art of the technology also has an impact on growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose a hundred people get told by an enthusiastic friend to try podcasting.
Of these, ten don’t have any hardware on which they can play the podcasts.
So the rest goes online, and tries to find interesting content, but only 50 people can find a directory in which they can even start to look for podcasts that they like. Only 40 people then find content that they sufficiently like.
Ten people drop out because they find loading the content too complicated. Of these, another ten find out that the files are too big for the hardware they have (for example in 2005, they just had a simple MP3 player, no iPod or similar).
Of the ones left, another five don’t have the patience for the downloads (we are talking dial-up internet access for a lot of people here, still).
If you have been keeping tabs: we are down to 25 people who are capable and willing to regularly listen to podcasts. Now suppose each of these tells four friends, on the average. That means we are back to a hundred.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Ways to Go Cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/value/three-ways-to-go-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 17:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/value/three-ways-to-go-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Public cloud migrations come in different shapes and sizes, but I see three major approaches. Each of these brings value in its own way, and they all have very different technical and governance implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-approaches&#34;&gt;Three approaches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies dying to get rid of their data centers often get started on a &lt;strong&gt;‘lift and shift’&lt;/strong&gt; approach, where applications are moved from existing servers to equivalent servers in the cloud. The cloud service model consumed here is mainly IaaS (infrastructure as a service). Not much is outsourced to cloud providers here. Contrast that with SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why lawyers need to understand cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/lawyers-need-understand-tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 13:54:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/lawyers-need-understand-tech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cloud is too important to leave to technical people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud distributes responsibility for IT services across an IT supply chain. This supply chain is composed of independent providers. This implies that there are these companies have &lt;strong&gt;technical boundaries&lt;/strong&gt; that are matched by organisational and &lt;strong&gt;contractual boundaries&lt;/strong&gt;. This is new, we did not have that before the digital revolution.
Amazon calls this the &lt;strong&gt;shared&lt;/strong&gt; responsibility model for cloud security.
I would simplify that as:  &lt;em&gt;what do I do, and what do you do&lt;/em&gt;? For example, who is responsible for patching the Operating System in an IaaS service model?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Organisation Size Matters - Dunbar&#39;s number</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/change/org-size-matters/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 20:45:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/change/org-size-matters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have worked with many organisations, large and small.
In one case, I implemented the exact same change in more than 15 organisations, whose size ranged from 35 to 35 thousand employees.
But that is a story for another unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It led me to see patterns in decision making and trust.
Who takes decisions in an organisation?
How do people even talk about decisions, especially when they concern digital technology?
Who do you trust?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promise Theory 3</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/promise-theory-part3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 05:58:14 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/promise-theory-part3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;origin story promise theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;suwinet
reisplanner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;design patterns&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;customer sevice, can I get a new app/user account&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: Can I get a unique IP address?
R: Here is your address, let me know when you are done with it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: thank you, I am done with this address&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example IP addresses allocation
&lt;img alt=&#34;alt text&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;image.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;alt text&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;image-1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example TCP/IP
picture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connect
Q: can you reserve buffer space for a connection?
R: yes we promise, here is your initial window size
A: thank you, here is your initial window size&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/unified-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 21:05:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/diginfra/unified-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The units so far have explored quite a few, seemingly randomly related, concepts and observations.
Here we&amp;rsquo;ll embed them in a unified theory that illustrates how they fit together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core is the concept of promise-based interactions between autonomous agents (human and technical). Every digital infrastructure can be understood as a network of these promises:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value Creation Layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promises made to consumers about service delivery (availability, performance)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economic models showing how shared resources and automation create value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business model frameworks showing how promises translate to revenue streams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Distribution Layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who makes which promises to whom (governance structures)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How promises are enforced (contracts, standards, regulations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control boundaries between agents (who decides what)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How scale shifts power dynamics (Dunbar&amp;rsquo;s number threshold effects)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risk Management Layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyzing what happens when promises are broken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vulnerabilities in promise networks (security, compliance)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust assumptions and zero trust principles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How externalities distribute risk across stakeholders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change Management Layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How promises evolve over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feedback loops that stabilize or destabilize systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology maturity cycles (from manual to automated)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disruption patterns when new agents enter the ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This model shows how these layers interact - for example, how power structures affect what promises can be made (value), how those promises create potential failure points (risk), and how adaptive change processes respond to those risks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimalisatie</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/home/optimalisatie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 06:59:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/home/optimalisatie/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disruptive Technologies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/powershift-disruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 21:25:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/powershift-disruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Technologies are often called disruptive.
But what makes a technology truly disruptive?
What has made the PC a disruptive technology? Or artificial intelligence, for that matter?
And at what time did it become a disruptive technology?
While many would accept that AI was a very disruptive technology starting from 2022 onwards,
most of it was available much earlier. GenAI, chatbots, etc.
Think of ELIZA, the 60s era psychology chatbot by Joseph Weizenbaum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Example Mermaid Client-Server</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/example-mermaid-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 11:21:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/example-mermaid-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;architecture-beta
    group frontend(cloud)[Frontend]
        service client(internet)[Client Browser] in frontend
    
    group backend(cloud)[Backend]
        service app_server(server)[Application Server] in backend
        service database(database)[Database] in backend
    
    client:B -- L:app_server
    app_server:B -- T:database
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big tech afhankelijkheid: wat is het echte risico?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/autonomie-van-bigtech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 09:36:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/autonomie-van-bigtech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Het nationale sentiment is negatief over de afhankelijkheid van &amp;lsquo;big tech&amp;rsquo;. Overheidsdata staat in een Amerikaanse cloud, we hebben geen eigen sociaal netwerk, enzovoort. En vergelijkbare sentimenten spelen bij andere organisaties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terecht wordt daarom nu op overheidsniveau een initiatief in gang gezet om wat aan die afhankelijkheid te doen. Dit initiatief staat ook bekend als &lt;a href=&#34;https://berthub.eu/articles/posts/cloud-kootwijk-moties-aangenomen/&#34;&gt;Cloud Kootwijk&lt;/a&gt;. Maar met een motie in de Kamer zijn we er nog niet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emoties zijn vaak een goede indicator, maar geen goede inhoudelijke analyse.
Ze leiden daarom nog wel eens tot beslissingen die onhandig, of zelfs contraproductief uitpakken. Hier legt de emotie wantrouwen bloot, maar waar die zich op richt moet een analyse uitwijzen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How My Site Got Hacked</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/how-my-site-got-hacked/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 15:35:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/how-my-site-got-hacked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;detection&#34;&gt;Detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have acted on the first signals more aggressively. But let’s talk about that later in this story.
Here is the story of my site being infected with malware, viewed by a professional cloud security expert. So I am going to apply all that cloud security theory to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hack led to business damage at the end of one of my webinars. In 2016, on a Friday, I did a webinar, at the end of which I had two links to my site as a call to action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Elements of Cloud Security</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 22:02:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/5-elements-of-cloud-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;five-elements-of-cloud-security&#34;&gt;Five elements of cloud security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, IT security started with &lt;strong&gt;infrastructure security&lt;/strong&gt;. Just protecting the data center was good enough. But that was before we had data communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When data started to escape the confines of the data center we needed to protect it. Typically through encryption. Hence we need &lt;strong&gt;data security&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the world wide web developed, we saw applications being exposed to it, and frankly, be vulnerable. So that is when &lt;strong&gt;application security&lt;/strong&gt; started to become more important.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How AI Can Help IT Risk Classification</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 19:45:36 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ai-risk-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How cool would it be to let an AI do some of the grunt work in analysing the risk of applications and services. This has the potential to speed up the work of risk assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, does it work in practice? Well, here is an example of AI-assisted risk classification. I downloaded some of the entries in the Dutch &lt;a href=&#34;https://algoritmes.overheid.nl/en&#34;&gt;algorithm register&lt;/a&gt;, which is a public register of systems that use algorithms. For each entry about 30 fields are available, including name, classification, owner, et cetera.
Some of the systems in the registry are AI-based. Indeed, we have AI to help check on AI&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Actors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/international-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/international-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The international arena has many actors that can influence digital infrastructures. But opinions differ on what the important ones are, or even what the relevant ones are.
But the international arena matters, because
by the nature of scaling, very few digital infrastructures are influenced by a single national actor only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word of clarification: I am using the word international here to mean all nations in the world, and their interrelations.
In US vernacular, the word international appears to mean all nations, except the US.
Instead, the word global is used to mean all nations, including the US.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The US Air Force Zero Trust Strategy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 12:26:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/airforce-zero-trust-strategy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Who is really doing Zero Trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the US Air Force is. Here is my summary, with some comments, of their strategy document for the benefit of my Certificate of Competence in Zero Trust (CCZT) learners. In fact, this is an edited version of a conversation we had during one of our classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the full strategy &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20API%20Reference%20Architecture%202.0.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the current roadmap &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/Portals/64/Documents/Strategy/DAF%20Enterprise%20Zero%20Trust%20Roadmap%20and%20Release%20Notes_v2.0.pdf?ver=36cbAKNEe7JiRVAPFwWepg%3d%3d&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, all linked from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dafcio.af.mil/&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the fundamental first important point about the strategy document is that it exists at all. There is an actual organization of significant size that has a strategy and is implementing it. Many can learn from this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snippets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/snippets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 12:05:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/snippets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Altijd bedenken: is er iets dat recent bij een klant is geweest?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heel veel NTS bij de logs van recente trainingen en workshops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wat is server en client? Bij X is bijvoorbeeld de server op de client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh ja, die discussie. Ben je verantwoordelijk als je onveilige software maakt, of alleen als je die als service beschikbaar stelt?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk: LMS 3-2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CERN data center&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;verhaal over corporate en MKB, maar ook individual, en society.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Infrastructures - the graphic novel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 14:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/graphic-novel-page1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the draft design of the graphic novel version of this book, which may or may not happen..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;digital world cyberpunk&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/dig-inf-front-page1.png&#34; title=&#34;With a little help from Dall-e&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can We Achieve Autonomy Over Our Digital Infrastructures?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 22:04:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-can-we-achieve-autonomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-our-own-cloud-kootwijk-rethinking-digital-sovereignty&#34;&gt;Building Our Own Cloud Kootwijk: Rethinking Digital Sovereignty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Netherlands, we are currently engaged in a heated debate about the undesirable dominance of big tech, particularly over a significant portion of the digital infrastructure of the Dutch government. This includes email, file storage, and many other forms of digital storage and processing—most of which are handled by American big tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure a similar debate is going on in many other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrofitting Zero Trust on an existing application: an illustration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 14:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/risk/retrofitting-zero-trust-existing-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust Architecture is an approach to better cybersecurity. To many, it seems daunting to implement. But it does not have to be hard to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this hypothetical situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an application with hundreds of thousands of sensitive records, let’s say client records. We assume that in this example it seems hard to implement MFA (Multi Factor Authentication) on it. What other controls can you implement to reduce the assumed trust? We can use the Kipling method, which is at the core of Zero Trust architectures, to engineer better controls. In short, the Kipling method is about the &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;what&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo;, etcetera of allowed communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mermaid diagram example</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 09:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/mermaid-example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A diagram should automagically appear here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;sequenceDiagram
    actor Client
    actor Provider
    Client-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Provider: Query
    Note right of Provider: Please promise me to bring a drink
    Provider-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Client: Ack
    Note right of Provider: I promise to bring you a drink in a short while
    Provider-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Client: Reply
    Note right of Provider: Please promise me that you are satisfied and will pay
    Client-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Provider: Ack
    Note right of Provider: I promise to pay you for the drink
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;%%  icons from https://iconify.design
architecture-beta
    group api(Storage)[API]

    service db(database)[Database] in api
    service disk1(disk)[Storage] in api
    service disk2(disk)[Storage] in api
    service server(server)[Server] in api

    db:L -- R:server
    disk1:T --&amp;gt; B:server
    disk2:T -- B:db
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;mermaid&#34;&gt;block-beta

in space llm:2 space out
in[&amp;#34;Prompt&amp;#34;] --&amp;gt; llm[&amp;#34;Large Language Model&amp;#34;]
llm--&amp;gt; out[&amp;#34;Completion&amp;#34;]

style in fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
style out fill:#fff,color:#000,line:#000;stroke-width:0px,color:#000,stroke-dasharray: 5 5
   
&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deployment diagrams for network security; fix this</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-diagram-fix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 17:09:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-diagram-fix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while back, I introduced my take on deployment diagrams for cloud and devops infrastructure. Some of the big points there are: it starts with intuitive drawings. Many people draw these things in similar ways, even without them having formal training.
In fact, formal training in architecture diagrams will not necessarily make those drawings easier to understand for the uninitiated.
But still. There are good drawings and there are drawings that can be improved.
My other big point is that deployment diagrams can be a great tool for security analysis. I am in some conversations with friends at banks who use them.
Recently I ran into the following example. Here is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://syang.substack.com/p/security-group-and-network-acl-in&#34;&gt;explanation of the difference between VPC and security groups&lt;/a&gt;. Great story, but I have some comments on the diagram, which used to come &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/vpc/latest/userguide/VPC_Security.html&#34;&gt;from AWS itself&lt;/a&gt;, by the way, but has been removed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Small Example of Cloud Native Development</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/tutorial-cloud-native/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 23:29:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/tutorial-cloud-native/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cloud-native software development enables new practices. But it also requires them. It is a new level of working. However, putting all these new practices together requires integrating a lot of pieces.
To illustrate this new approach, I have started to develop a minimal application. Although minimal, I run it in production. Its basic function is to regularly pull out data from an air quality sensor into a cloud-based database. Together it is a few hundred lines of code.
Here are the major features of the example:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top 8 cloud risks according to ENISA</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-8-cloud-risks-according-to-enisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 09:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/top-8-cloud-risks-according-to-enisa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does security in the cloud ever bother you? It would be weird if it didn’t. Cloud computing has a lot of benefits, but also a lot of risks if done in the wrong way.
So what are the most important risks? The European Network Information Security Agency did extensive research on that in 2009 already, and identified 35 risk categories. This analysis is used by a number of players in the industry, including certain banking regulators. From those 35, ENISA has selected 8 as the most relevant ones. This article explains them, not in any particular order. (And by the way: ENISA is pronounced as ‘eniesa’, not ‘enaiza’).
You can also get the story on my YouTube video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Cloud Sprawl in 2012</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/stopping-senseless-sprawl-of-private-clouds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 07:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/cases/stopping-senseless-sprawl-of-private-clouds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A 2012 case study&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in a cloud world, reducing server count is a lofty goal in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, you would be paying for all those servers anyway. Understand that sticking all your servers in a private cloud makes them more flexible, but not necessarily more efficient or cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2012 I did an interview with a guy who has a full time job in keeping those server counts down. Ron Kaminski is a capacity planner at Kimberly Clark Corporation (KCC). This interview is a composite of several conversations I had with Ron at the annual Computer Measurement Group (CMG) conferences, and a number of messages Ron wrote.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directories are also infrastructures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/directories-are-also-infrastructures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2006 10:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/directories-are-also-infrastructures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the big projects I am working on right now (2006) is directory services for identity management. In these directories digital identities such as loginnames, addresses, access rights, etc. are stored. With an adequately structured directory service, the proper management of access rights becomes a lot easier, which translates into cost savings and better security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of these include the internet&amp;rsquo;s Domain Name System (DNS) and Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Active Directory. A lot of organizations however, have requirements beyond these systems, and for these a wide range of custom solutions are used.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Neutrality: who pays the ferryman?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-neutrality-who-pays-the-ferryman/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2006 13:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/network-neutrality-who-pays-the-ferryman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Network neutrality has become the topic of intense discussion and legislative action.&lt;br&gt;
See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/01/21/AR2006012100094.html&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; , a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_neutrality&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circleid.com/posts/network_neutrality/&#34;&gt;CircelID&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the issue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand people argue for &amp;lsquo;universal service&amp;rsquo; that say that one person&amp;rsquo;s bits should not be treated differently from another person&amp;rsquo;s. This compares to the idea that the phone company should not be allowed to treat your calls differently depending on what you want to say, or that red haired people would have a different monthly fee. There are laws against this type of discrimination (at least in most nations), and some people want to extend this law to Internet traffic. On the other hand there are some Internet providers who want to charge different customers different rates for different service. &amp;ldquo;We can&amp;rsquo;t have companies freeloading on our expensive pipes&amp;rdquo;, they claim.
Clearly we seem to want both. We don&amp;rsquo;t want the phone companies to decide which traffic gets carried, and we also don’t want a bland one-size-fits-all service that is expensive for some and inadequate for others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
