<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Power on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Power on Digital Infrastructures at Scale</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:31:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/book/power/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Power</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/intro-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:31:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/intro-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Power is a concept that is widely used and ill defined. Many philosophers have discussed it, but not one definition really stands out.
Before we attempt to define power formally, let&amp;rsquo;s see how the word in used in everyday IT situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding power in IT is not just academic. As the examples show it is crucial in understanding how IT works, and creates value and risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cloud architect held significant power in deciding which platforms the organization would adopt for its digital transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated deployment pipelines gave development teams the power to release software faster and with fewer errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legacy systems often retain unexpected power in large organizations, simply because so many critical processes still depend on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regulators have the power to halt digital initiatives if data protection requirements are not met.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By owning the central identity management service, the security team had the power to control access across the entire infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outages at major cloud providers show how concentrated power in digital infrastructures can lead to systemic risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CIO used the power of budget approval to steer the enterprise toward adopting more secure infrastructure patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power struggles between central IT and business units can delay the rollout of shared infrastructure services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With real-time observability tools, operations teams gained the power to detect and respond to incidents before users were affected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open-source community can collectively wield more power than a single vendor when shaping the direction of a software tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these examples, we can see certain recurring features of power in the context of IT and digital infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positions of Power in IT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 11:06:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/positions-of-power-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the key aspirations of Digital Infrastructures at Scale is to equip you with the tools to shape and drive change in your professional environment—especially when your goal is to lead a transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important positions of influence in IT are architects and auditors/assessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IT architects are builders. They design new applications, platforms, and infrastructures that enable businesses to operate more effectively. A CRM system, for example, is not just a technical solution—it transforms workflows, communication, and decision-making. Similarly, infrastructure architects create digital foundations that accelerate the deployment of such applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who made podcasting big?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/the-tipping-point-for-podcasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2005 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/the-tipping-point-for-podcasting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Podcasting has its own digital infrastructures, for example in hosting them.
Let&amp;rsquo;s look at how podcasting has grown, and what made it take off anyway?
Many actors influence each other here, and the state of the art of the technology also has an impact on growth rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose a hundred people get told by an enthusiastic friend to try podcasting.
Of these, ten don’t have any hardware on which they can play the podcasts.
So the rest goes online, and tries to find interesting content, but only 50 people can find a directory in which they can even start to look for podcasts that they like. Only 40 people then find content that they sufficiently like.
Ten people drop out because they find loading the content too complicated. Of these, another ten find out that the files are too big for the hardware they have (for example in 2005, they just had a simple MP3 player, no iPod or similar).
Of the ones left, another five don’t have the patience for the downloads (we are talking dial-up internet access for a lot of people here, still).
If you have been keeping tabs: we are down to 25 people who are capable and willing to regularly listen to podcasts. Now suppose each of these tells four friends, on the average. That means we are back to a hundred.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Actors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/book/power/international-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 17:56:28 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/book/power/international-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The international arena has many actors that can influence digital infrastructures. But opinions differ on what the important ones are, or even what the relevant ones are.
But the international arena matters, because
by the nature of scaling, very few digital infrastructures are influenced by a single national actor only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word of clarification: I am using the word international here to mean all nations in the world, and their interrelations.
In US vernacular, the word international appears to mean all nations, except the US.
Instead, the word global is used to mean all nations, including the US.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
